{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "One of these people served under Felix Dzerzhinsky before becoming a defendant at the Trial of the Twenty-One. Another one of these people proposed the Katyn Massacre. Another one of these people names a period of political repression he presided over and is nicknamed “The Vanishing Commissar” after he was airbrushed out of official pictures. Genrikh Yagoda, Lavrenty Beria, and Nikolai Yezhov all served in, for ten points, what position, the head of Soviet intelligence under Stalin? ANSWER:head of the NKVD(acceptPeople’s Commissar for Internal Affairs,acceptequivalents for “head”, do not accept or prompt on “head of the KGB” or “head of the Cheka” or “head of the GPU”) (2) Charles Floyd was the only member of this group to die, likely the result of a ruptured appendix. The path of this group was traced due to leftover mercury in the soil, a side effect of mercury-based, high-powered laxatives called “Dr. Rush’s Bilious Pills.” Jean Baptiste Charbonneau was born into this group, the son of a French-Canadian prisoner and a Shoshone woman. Sacajawea was a member of, for ten points, what group tasked by Thomas Jefferson with exploring the newly purchased Louisiana Territory?",
      "answer": [
        "Lewis and Clark Expedition",
        "Corps of Discovery"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This dynasty won an early victory at the Battle of the Zab. This dynasty was established in a revolution led by the Persian general Abu Muslim. One ruler from this dynasty gave Charlemagne gifts including a clock and an elephant. That ruler was Harun al-Rashid, who may have established the House of Wisdom to house his library. For ten points, name this caliphate whose capital of Baghdad was sacked by the Mongols in 1258, the successors of the Umayyads.",
      "answer": "Abbasid Caliphate"
    },
    {
      "question": "A strike of workers gathering this resource in Anzin inspired Zola’s novel Germinal. The first railroads in Continental Europe transported this resource from Saint-Etienne. Iron production was greatly increased by substituting wood with a processed form of this resource. The “sea” form of this resource was used in locomotives and is graded between this resource’s anthracite and bituminous forms. Coke is a form of, for ten points, what carbon-based rock which fueled the Industrial Revolution?",
      "answer": "coal"
    },
    {
      "question": "A holder of this posistion called the U.S. “more a Tale of Two Cities than a shining city on a hill” as the keynote speaker at the 1984 DNC. Another holder of this position defeated Carl Paladino in 2010 and established the Excelsior scholarship for his state’s public universities. That holder of this non-municipal position called Jeff Bezos to attempt to salvage a deal that would create an Amazon HQ2 in Long Island City. For ten points, name this gubernatorial position held by Mario and Andrew Cuomo.",
      "answer": "governor of New York"
    },
    {
      "question": "This composer wrote a long, one movement work dedicated to Robert Schumann, an example of double function form. This composer, who wrote piano transcriptions for all nine Beethoven symphonies, pioneered the genre of symphonic poem with works such as Les Pr´eludes. In the 1840s, the popularity of this composer throughout Europe led to a namesake “mania.” For ten points, name this composer of the Mephisto Waltzes, Hungarian Rhapsodies, and Transcendental Etudes.",
      "answer": "Franz Liszt"
    },
    {
      "question": "The leader of one side in this battle rejected Alfred Terry’s offer of gattling guns, preferring to stay a mobile force. During this battle, William W. Cooke sent a “last message” begging Frederick Benteen to quickly “Bring Packs.” Myles Keogh’s horse, Comanche, was one of the only surviving members of the US military at the end of this battle. For ten points, name this 1876 battle of the Great Sioux War, the last stand of the 7th Calvary under George Custer.",
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Little Bighorn",
        "Battle of the Greasy Grass",
        "Custer’s Last Stand before “last” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Lu Haodong was executed for leading an insurgency in this city, the first of a series of uprisings prior to the Xinhai Revolution. This city’s Thirteen Factories became integral to a trade monopoly run by the cohong guilds, which served this city’s namesake system. Lin Zexu’s attempt to destroy the opium trade in this city prompted Britain to send an expedition to nearby Hong Kong. The First Opium War was sparked in, for ten points, what coastal city that names a major Chinese dialect?",
      "answer": "Canton or Guangzhou,"
    },
    {
      "question": "This speech begins by asking the listener to “avoid the impulse to live only for today.” The deliverer of this speech defended his increased funding of scientific research but warned that public policy could become captive to a “scientific-technological elite.” This speech notes that, at one time, plowshares could be relied on to make swords, but that this is no longer the case. For ten points, name this final speech by the 34th President of the United States which warned against the rise of the military-industrial complex.",
      "answer": "Eisenhower’s farewell address"
    },
    {
      "question": "Lynn Hunt argued that these concepts grew out of a shift in mentality influenced by reading popular novels. John Locke argued the divinity of humans as God’s creations formed the basis for the natural kind of these concepts. One work named for these concepts argued that these concepts could never be revoked by government, which was instead supposed to protect them, and was written by Thomas Paine. A 1948 UN Declaration tried to formulate, for ten points, what basic universal freedoms?",
      "answer": "Human rights"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2007, this man’s representatives at 19 Entertainment cherry-picked numbers to announce a supposed $250 million contract. This man, who donated his entire salary at Paris Saint-Germain to charity in 2013, received the OBE in 2003 from Queen Elizabeth II. This partial owner of the upcoming MLS team Inter Miami CF is married to Victoria Adams, a former Spice Girl. This man’s move to the LA Galaxy spurred American interest in soccer. For ten points, name this English midfielder, well known for his ability to “bend” kicks.",
        "answer": "David Beckham"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1998, Paris Saint-Germain refused to leave the Parc des Princes in favor of this venue, which was built for the 1998 World Cup. The November 2015 attacks in Paris targeted this building, which was hosting a friendly between Germany and France.",
        "answer": "Stade de France"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this state, Ed Jackson offered governor Warren McCray a $10,000 bribe to corrupt public offices. Madge Oberholtzer was kidnapped from a train station in this state and ultimately murdered by D.C. Stephenson. A gangster imprisoned in this state used a fake gun to escape from the Crown Point jail. This state’s city of Evansville was the birth place of its own branch of the Ku Klux Klan. Illinois borders, for ten points, what state where John Dillinger robbed a bank in East Chicago?",
        "answer": "Indiana"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "As head of a state branch of the KKK, D.C. Stephenson officially held this title, a majority of which was needed to elect a Grand Wizard.",
        "answer": "Grand Dragon"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "If this country were to unite with its neighbor, the region of Gagauzia would gain right to self- determination. Russia banned importing wines from this country and Georgia in 2006 after this country rejected the Kozak memorandum, which would have created an “assymetric” state to deal with its breakaway province of Transnistria. Much of Bessarabia is contained in, for ten points, what Eastern European nation along the Dnieper River that chose not to join Romania.",
        "answer": "Republic of Moldova"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A major 1903 pogrom in this largest Moldovan city led Theodor Herzl to propose the Uganda Scheme for Jewish resettlement.",
        "answer": [
          "Chisinau",
          "Kishinev"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An attack on this island by French forces under Sebastien Lespes was described by Canadian missionary George Mackay. Antonius Hambroek was executed after urging a garrison on this island to fight on. The Keelung [jee-loeng] Campaign took place on this island, where Dutch forces were defeated at the Siege of Fort Zeelandia. This island’s Hoklo population are descended from Qing-era colonizers from neighboring Fujian Province. For ten points, name this autonomous island governed by the Republic of China.",
        "answer": [
          "Taiwan",
          "Formosa"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This loyalist Ming admiral defeated the Dutch at the Siege of Fort Zeelandia and created the Kingdom of Tungning.",
        "answer": [
          "Koxinga",
          "Zheng Chenggong"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2014, Thomas Hales’ team finished their work proving a conjecture named for this man. English astronomer and explorer Thomas Harriot corresponded with this man about optics and cannonball stacking, the latter of which inspired this man’s namesake conjecture about sphere packing. Albrecht von Wallenstein was advised astrologically by this man, whose works like Harmonices Mundi and Astronomia Nova were influenced by his work for Tycho Brahe. For ten points, name this German mathematician and astronomer who developed the three laws of planetary motion.",
        "answer": "Johannes Kepler"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Thomas Harriot explored the New World on behalf of this patron, who hired him as a tutor and accountant. Harriot and this man discussed the cannonball problem, whose solution states that the only perfect square integers that can represent the number of cannonballs stacked in a square pyramid are 1 and 4900.",
        "answer": "Sir Walter Raleigh"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This monarch was forced to dismiss one mistress when she was blamed for a life-threatening illness while he was visiting troops in Metz. That woman, the Duchess of Chateauroux, was one of four Mailly sisters who were mistresses to this monarch, who appointed the Duc de Choiseul as prime minister due to the influence of his most famous mistress. A former courtesan, Madame du Barry, was the scandalous last mistress of, for ten points, what French monarch, who also loved Madame de Pompadour?",
        "answer": "Louis XV"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A wave of popular literature attacking Louis XV’s mistresses was related to earlier works published during the Fronde attacking and named for what minister of Louis XIII and XIV?",
        "answer": "Cardinal Jules Mazarin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While at the title location of this book, characters use spoons to steal malt syrup from a factory line. As a child, the protagonist of this book is thrown in a YMCA swimming pool by his father. That character later goes on to have a child with Montana Wildhack. The protagonist of this book is taken prisoner after the Battle of the Bulge and is displayed in a zoo by a race of aliens called Tralfamadorians. For ten points, name this novel about Billy Pilgrim, written by Kurt Vonnegut.",
        "answer": "Slaughterhouse-Five or The Childrens’ Crusade: A Duty Dance with Death"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Vonnegut’s first novel, Player Piano, satirizes this company, which produced turbochargers for the B-17 Flying Fortress and was founded by Thomas Edison.",
        "answer": [
          "General Electric Company",
          "GE"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This politician was inspired by the Quakers to appoint Ely S. Parker as his Commissioner for Indian Affairs. Benjamin Bristow resigned as Secretary of the Treasury after a conflict with this man’s personal secretary. The concept of international arbitration was developed by this man’s Secretary of State, Hamilton Fish, who dealt with the Virginius affair. For ten points, name this 18th President of the United States, a decorated Union general.",
        "answer": "Ulysses S. Grant"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Benjamin Bristow came into conflict with Grant’s personal secretary over a tax scandal affecting this good.",
        "answer": "whiskey"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Haymarket Square Riot",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "City in which the bombing and riot took place.",
          "answer": "Chicago"
        },
        {
          "question": "Month in which the riot took place; the affair inspired International Workers’ Day, on the first day of this month.",
          "answer": [
            "May",
            "May Day"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Specific labor policy that workers agitated for via a general strike leading up to the riot.",
          "answer": "eight-hour work day"
        },
        {
          "question": "Labor group, led by Terence Powderly, whose membership plummeted after the riot.",
          "answer": "Noble and Holy Order of the Knights of Labor"
        },
        {
          "question": "Activist and publisher of the Arbeiter-Zeitung who spoke at the square and was executed for accessory to murder.",
          "answer": "August Spies"
        },
        {
          "question": "Farm machinery company whose plant was the site of protests the day before the riot.",
          "answer": "McCormick Harvesting Machine Company"
        },
        {
          "question": "Governor who pardoned three of the condemned and was voted out of office 4 years later.",
          "answer": "John Peter Altgeld"
        },
        {
          "question": "Anarchist whose apartment was searched for bomb-making materials; he committed suicide before his execution.",
          "answer": "Louis Lingg"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Catherine the Great",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country where she ruled as Empress for over three decades.",
          "answer": "Russia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Husband of Catherine who was overthrown in 1762.",
          "answer": "Peter III"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gemstone, named for Orlov, placed in Catherine’s scepter. A blue one of these is named for the Hope family.",
          "answer": "diamond"
        },
        {
          "question": "Two-word term for absolute monarchs like Catherine who supported education, healthcare, and other progressive ideals.",
          "answer": "enlightened despotism"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lover of Catherine who helped negotiate the end of a war against Turkey and names a famous battleship.",
          "answer": [
            "Grigory Potemkin",
            "Battleship Potemkin"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Lover of Catherine, who helped him become king of Poland in 1764.",
          "answer": [
            "Stanislaw Poniatowski",
            "Stanislaw II Augustus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Co-editor, with Diderot, of the Encyclop´edie; his work on wave equations was supported by Catherine.",
          "answer": "Jean-Baptiste le Rond d’Alembert"
        },
        {
          "question": "Treaty that ended war with Turkey in 1792, signed in Moldavia.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Jassy"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Singapore",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country it was part of until 1965, when it was expelled.",
          "answer": "Malaysia"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Prime Minister of independent Singapore, who famously cried upon its expulsion.",
          "answer": "Lee Kuan Yew"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political party that has led Singapore since its independence.",
          "answer": [
            "People’s Action Party",
            "PAP"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Largest opposition party in Singapore; it shares its name with North Korea’s ruling party",
          "answer": "Worker’s Party"
        },
        {
          "question": "Punishment used in Singapore on American teenager Michael Fay in 1994 for vandalism.",
          "answer": [
            "caning",
            "descriptions of being beaten with a cane"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "British explorer who is considered the founder of modern Singapore.",
          "answer": "Sir Stamford Raffles"
        },
        {
          "question": "Famous landmark in Singapore’s Bayfront area consisting of three towers connected by a rooftop SkyPark.",
          "answer": "Marina Bay Sands"
        },
        {
          "question": "First Viceroy of India, who names an early British fort built on the grounds of the original governor’s mansion.",
          "answer": [
            "Charles John Canning",
            "Earl Canning",
            "Viscont Canning",
            "Fort Canning Hill"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Goldsmiths gave 76 paintings as annual offerings to this building, its Great Mays. The twelve apostles are placed in a circle around Christ at the center of this building’s 84-panel western (20 pts)",
        "rose window, which was created by this building’s first architect, Jehan de Chelles. A statue of Saint Thomas on this building’s spire bore resemblance to this building’s renovator, Eug`ene (10 pts)",
        "Viollet-le-Duc, who also replaced this building’s gargoyles. That spire was destroyed in a 2019 fire that also largely destroyed this building’s roof. For ten points, name this cathedral in Paris."
      ],
      "answer": "Notre Dame de Paris"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) An inscription tells of how one leader of this empire had the southern ocean “perfumed by the breezes” of his skills. Xuanzang and (20 pts)",
        "Faxian were both Chinese visitors in this empire, during which caturanga, an early form of chess, and base ten numerals were first developed. Harisena served as a minister in this empire and created the (10 pts)",
        "Allahabad Pillar. The playwright Kalidasa and astronomer Aryabhata lived in this empire which was centered at Pataliputra. For ten points, name this empire that lasted from the 3rd century to 543 in India."
      ],
      "answer": "Gupta Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 1945, Japanese Americans in an internment camp near this city rioted after three men were to be moved. The Republic of Texas sent a failed expedition to claim this city in 1841. A railway partially named for this city, (20 pts)",
        "Atchison and Topeka, never actually reached this city, which was established by Don Pedro de Peralta. Pedro Vial pioneered a (10 pts)",
        "trail to this city which was officially established by William Becknell. Pueblo Indian pottery is sold in this city, where Pop´e led his revolt. For ten points, name this capital of New Mexico."
      ],
      "answer": "Santa Fe"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this conflict, Robin Olds commanded Operation Bolo, which successfully lured enemy fighters away from the more vulnerable Thuds. One politician’s promise that (20 pts)",
        "“peace is at hand” ironically prompted the launching of Linebacker II during this war, which was mockingly called the Christmas bombings. Carrier-based alpha strikes were first adopted during this conflict’s (10 pts)",
        "Rolling Thunder campaign, whose high casualty rate forced the US Navy to develop its TOPGUN program. For ten points, name this conflict in which heavy bombing damaged the Ho Chi Minh Trail and the Hanoi area."
      ],
      "answer": "Vietnam War"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) According to the Akal Takht, women are not allowed to sing hymns in the holiest temple of this religion. Members of this religion have a combination of sugar and water called (20 pts)",
        "“amrit” splashed in their eyes during the baptism ceremony. Many leaders of this religion were served by Baba Buddha. Members of this religion are required to keep the Five Ks when they are baptized into the (10 pts)",
        "Khalsa. Followers of this religion wear the “pagh” or “dastaar” to cover their “kesh,” or uncut hair. For ten points, name this South Asian religion founded by Guru Nanak."
      ],
      "answer": "Sikhism"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) With John Marshall, this man represented American debtors in the case of Ware v. Hylton. This governor granted a charter to (20 pts)",
        "Hampden-Sydney College for which he served as a trustee with James Madison. In one case, this man convinced a jury to return only a penny of damages in (10 pts)",
        "Parson’s Cause. This man deliver an impassioned defense of the Virginia Resolves. This man rallied against Federalism as the first post-colonial governor of Virginia. For ten points, name this man who, at the 2nd Virginia Convention, said “Give me liberty, or give me death.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Patrick Henry"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Anton Drexler founded one predecessor to this political party, the Free Workers’ Committee for a Good Peace. An extension of old-age pensions and land reforms to justify expropriating land were two of this political party’s (20 pts)",
        "25-Point Program, which were introduced in a speech at the Hofbr¨auhaus. This party’s associated militia would occasionally beat up political opponents outside the (10 pts)",
        "beer halls where this party held rallies and were called the “brownshirts.” Capitalism, Bolshevism, and Jews were frequent targets of, for ten points, what political party led by Adolf Hitler?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Nazi Party",
        "Nationalsocializtische Deutsche Arbeiterpartei",
        "NSDAP,",
        "National Socialist German Worker’s Party"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A law code of these people, the Liber ludiciorum, was promulgated by Chindasuinth and later expanded by Recceswinth. A ruler of these people received a fragment of the true cross after he renounced Arianism at the Third Council of (20 pts)",
        "Toledo. Defeat to Clovis I at the Battle of Vouill´e [vwee-YAY] forced these people to leave their capital at (10 pts)",
        "Toulouse. These people inadvertently inspired St. Augustine to write The City of God after their ruler Alaric sacked Rome in 410. For ten points, name these Germanic people related to the Ostrogoths."
      ],
      "answer": "Visigoths"
    }
  ]
}